truth. CHAPTER 6 THERE WAS someone CRYING— —THERE WAS!" The next day the rain poured down in
torrents again, and when Mary looked out of her window the Moore was almost
hidden by gray mist and cloud. There could be no going out
today What do you do in your cottage when it rains like this?" she asked Martha.
"Try to keep from under each other's feet mostly," Martha
answered hey there does seem a lot of us then. Mother's a good-tempered woman but
she gets fair moyed The biggest ones goes out in the Cow Shed and plays there
dick and he doesn't mind the wet. He goes out just the same as if the sun was
shining He says he sees things on rainy days as doesn't show when it's fair
weather. He once found a little fox cub half drowned in its hole ho and he
brought it home in the bosom of his shirt to keep it
warm. Its mother had been killed nearby and the hole was swam out and the rest
of the litter was dead. He's got it at home now. He found a half drowned young
crow another time and he brought it home, too and tamed it. It's named Soot because
it's so black and it hops and flies about with him everywhere." The time had come when Mary
had forgotten to resent Martha's familiar talk. She had even begun to find
it interesting and to be sorry when she stopped or went
away. The stories she had been told by her Aya when she lived in India had been
quite unlike those Martha had to tell about the Morland cottage which held 14
people who lived in four little rooms and never had quite enough to eat. The
children seemed to tumble about and amuse themselves like a litter of rough, good-natured collie
puppies. Mary was most attracted by the mother and Dickon. When Martha told
stories of what "mother" said or did they always sounded
comfortable. "If I had a raven or a fox cuup I could play with it," said Mary. "But
I have nothing." Martha looked perplexed. "Can that knit?" she
asked. "No," answered Mary. "Can th so No." "Can thou read?"
"Yes." "Then why doesn't thou read something or learn a bit of spelling thst old
enough to be learning thy book a good bit now." "I haven't any books," said Mary.
"Those I had were left in India." "That's a pity," said Martha. "If Mrs
Medlock let thee go into the library, there's thousands of books there." Mary
did not ask where the library was, because she was sudden ly inspired by a
new idea. She made up her mind to go and find it herself. She was not troubled
about Mrs. Medlock. Mrs. Medlock seemed always to be in her comfortable housekeeper sitting room
downstairs In this queer place one scarcely ever saw anyone at all. In fact,
there was no one to see but the servants, and when their master was away they
lived a luxurious life below stairs, where there was a huge kitchen hung
about with shining brass and putor and a large servants' hall where there were
four or five abundant meals eaten every day, and where a great deal of lively
romping went on when Mrs. Medlock was out of the way. Mary's meals were served regularly,
and Martha waited on her, but no one troubled themselves about her in the
least. Mrs. Medlock came and looked at her every day or two, but no one inquired
what she did or told her what to do. She supposed that perhaps this was the
English way of treating children. In India she had always been
attended by her Aya who had followed her about and waited on her, hand and foot.
She had often been tired of her company.
Now she was followed by nobody and was learning to dress herself because Martha
looked as though she thought she was silly and stupid when she wanted to have
things handed to her and put on. "Hasn't that got good sense?" she said once, when
Mary had stood waiting for her to put on her gloves for her. "Our Susan Anne is
twice as sharp as thee and she's only 4 year' old. Sometimes th looks fair soft in the
head." Mary had worn her contrary scowl for an hour after that, but it made her
think several entirely new things. She stood at the window for about
10 minutes this morning after Martha had swept up the hearth for the last time
and gone downstairs She was thinking over the new idea which
had come to her when she heard of the library. She did not care very much about
the library itself, because she had read very few books; but to hear of it brought back to
her mind the hundred rooms with closed doors. She wondered if they were all
really locked and what she would find if she could get into any of them. Were
there a hundred really? Why shouldn't she go and see how many doors she could
count? It would be something to do on this morning when she could not go
out. She had never been taught to ask permission to do things, and she knew
nothing at all about authority, so she would not have thought it necessary to
ask Mrs. Medlock if she might walk about the house, even if she had seen
her. She opened the door of the room and went into the corridor, and then she
began her her wanderings. It was a long corridor and it branched into other corridors and it led
her up short flights of steps which mounted to others again. There were doors and doors, and
there were pictures on the walls. Sometimes they were pictures of
dark, curious landscapes, but oftenest they were portraits of men and women in
queer, grand costumes made of satin and velvet. She found found herself in one
long gallery whose walls were covered with these portraits. She had never
thought there could be so many in any house. She walked slowly down this place
and stared at the faces which also seemed to stare at her. She felt as if
they were wondering what a little girl from India was doing in their house. Some
were pictures of children— —little girls in thick satin frocks which reached to
their feet and stood out about them, and boys with puffed sleeves and lace
collars and long hair, or with big roughs around their necks. She always stopped to
look at the children, and wonder what their names were, and where they had gone,
and why they wore such odd clothes. There was a stiff, plain little girl rather like
herself. She wore a green bade dress and held a green parrot on her finger. Her
eyes had a sharp, curious look.
"Where do you live now?" said Mary aloud to her. "I wish you were
here." Surely no other little girl ever spent such a queer morning. It seemed as
if there was no one in all the huge rambling house but her own small self,
wandering about upstairs and down, through narrow passages and wide ones,
where it seemed to her that no one but herself had ever
walked. Since so many rooms had been built, people must have lived in them, but
it all seemed so empty that she could not quite believe it
true. It was not until she climbed to the second floor that she thought of turning
the handle of a door. All the doors were shut, as Mrs. Medlock had said they were,
but at last she put her hand on the handle of one of them and turned
it. She was almost frightened for a moment when she felt that it turned
without difficulty and that when she pushed upon the door itself it slowly and heavily
opened. It was a massive door and opened into a big bedroom. There were embroidered hangings
on the wall, and inlaid furniture such as she had seen in India stood about the
room. A broad window with leaded panes looked out upon the Moore and over the
mantle was another portrait of the stiff, plain little girl who seemed to stare at
her more curiously than ever. "Perhaps she slept here once," said
Mary. "She stares at me so that she makes me feel queer." After that she opened more
doors and more. She saw so many rooms that she became quite tired and began to
think that there must be a hundred, though she had not counted them. In all
of them there were old pictures or old tapestries with strange scenes worked on
them. There were curious pieces of furniture and curious ornaments in
nearly all of them. In one room, which looked like a lady's sitting room the
hangings were all embroidered velvet, and in a cabinet were about a hundred little
elephants made of ivory. They were of different sizes, and some had their mots
or penquins on their backs. Some were much bigger than the others and some
were so tiny that they seemed only babies. Mary had seen carved ivory in
India and she knew all about elephants. She opened the door of the
cabinet and stood on a foot stol and played with these for quite a long
time. When she got tired she set the elephants in order and shut the door of the
cabinet. In all her wanderings through the long corridors in the empty rooms,
she had seen nothing alive; but in this room room she saw
something. Just after she had closed the cabinet door she heard a tiny rustling
sound. It made her jump and look around at the sofa by the
fireplace, from which it seemed to come.
In the corner of the sofa there was a cushion, and in the velvet which covered
it there was a hole, and out of the hole peeped a tiny head with a pair of
frightened eyes in it. Mary crept softly across the room to look. The bright eyes
belonged to a little gray mouse, and the mouse had eaten a hole into the cushion
and made a comfortable nest there. Six baby mice were cuddled up asleep near
her. If there was no one else alive in the hundred rooms there were seven mice
who did not look lonely at all. "If they wouldn't be so frightened I
would take them back with me," said Mary.
She had wandered about long enough to feel too tired to wander any farther, and
she turned back. Two or three times she lost her way by turning down the wrong
corridor and was obliged to ramble up and down until she found the right one;
but at last she reached her own floor again, though she was some distance from
her own room and did not know exactly where she was. "I believe I have taken a wrong
turning again," she said, standing still at what seemed the end of a short passage
with tapestry on the wall. "I don't know which way to go. How still everything is!"
It was while she was standing here and just after she had said this that the
stillness was broken by a sound. It was another cry, but not quite like the one
she had heard last night; it was only a short one, a fretful, childish wine
muffled by passing through walls.
"It's nearer than it was," said Mary, her heart beating rather faster. "And it is
crying." She put her hand accidentally upon the tapestry near her, and then
sprang back, feeling quite startled. The tapestry was the covering of a door
which fell open and showed her that there was another part of the corridor
behind it, and Mrs. Medlock was coming up it with her bunch of keys in her hand
and a very cross look on her face.
"What are you doing here?" she said, and she took Mary by the arm and pulled her away.
"What did I tell you?" "I turned around the wrong corner," explained Mary. "I didn't
know which way to go and I heard someone crying." She quite hated Mrs. Medlock at
the moment, but she hated her more the next. "You didn't hear anything of the
sort," said the housekeeper. "You come along back to your own nursery or I'll box your ears."
And she took her by the arm and half pushed, half pulled her up one passage
and down another until she pushed her in at the door of her own
room. "Now," she said, "you stay where you're told to stay or you'll find yourself
locked up. The master had better get you a governor same as he said he would.
You're one that needs someone to look sharp after you. I've got enough to do."
She went out of the room and slammed the door after her, and Mary went and sat on
the Hearth rug pale with rage. She did not cry, but ground her teeth. "There was
someone crying— —there was —there was she said to herself. She had heard it twice
now, and sometime she would find out. She had found out a great deal this morning.
She felt as if she had been on a long journey, and at any rate she had had
something to amuse her all the time, and she had played with the ivory elephants
and had seen the gray mouse and its babies in their nest in the velvet
cushion. CHAPTER 7 THE KEY OF THE